Welcome back to the Centrifuge, where we
apply studies to back or refute claims
made on health shows. In this episode,
we'll be doing a continuation of Dr.
Robert Lustik's take on fructose. Now,
there is an earlier episode, but you
don't need to have watched that one to
watch this one. In this episode, Dr.
Lustik, a guest on the Huberman podcast
and professor of pediatric
endocrinology, makes a few strong
claims. One, fructose blocks three
critical mitochondrial enzymes acting as
a mitochondrial poison. Two, eating
fructose long-term leads to death. And
three, fructose causes a longevity tax,
shortening our life. Now, as usual,
you'll find a summary at the end,
studies linked for you, and chapters to
skip through for your convenience. Let's
spin it.
>> And let me tell you why it's
problematic. We haven't gotten to that
yet. We're just talking about whether
it's vestigial versus needed. Now, let's
talk about what fructose does.
Turns out fructose inhibits three, count
them, three separate enzymes necessary
for normal mitochondrial function. Now,
I your mitochondria make ATP. Your
mitochondria have to work at peak
efficiency. That's what metabolic health
is. Is mitochondria working at peak
efficiency? Well, there are three
enzymes that are inhibited by fructose.
Number one, AMKinase.
All right. Now, AMKinase is the fuel
gauge on the liver cell. It's the thing
that tells the liver to make more
mitochondria, fresher mitochondria.
Because if your AM levels are high, that
means you've defospholated a bunch of
ATPs and you have to regenerate them.
So, you need some more mitochondria. So,
it's a negative feedback pathway. Well,
you need that AMP kinase to generate
that mitochondrial biogenesis signal.
Except that fructose, a metabolite of
fructose called methyl gyioxil MGO
sits in the active site of the gamma
subunit of that ammp kynise and actually
binds to arginines in that active site
rendering that
uh u enzyme now dead. It's an
irreversible inhibition because of the
covealent bonding of that methylioxil
that aldahhide to the arginine and now
that enzyme is dead.
>> Okay. So it basically acts like a key
that doesn't turn the lock but prevents
the the key that you want in that lock
from entering the the lock.
>> It's like it's like gluing a lock shut.
>> Yeah.
>> Got it. All right.
>> So that's one of the enzymes.
>> That's one.
>> Okay.
>> Second one. AAD L asal COA dehydrogenase
longchain. So this is necessary to
cleave two carbon fragments off fatty
acids to prepare them for u uh
metabolism.
So inhibits that one. And then finally
it inhibits carnitine palmol transferase
1. Now CPT1 now that's the enzyme that
regenerates carnitine. carnitine is the
shuttle mechanism by which you get the
uh fatty acids from the outer
mitochondrial membrane through to the
inner mitochondrial membrane so that
they can be beta oxidized for energy. So
if you don't have that C uh CPT1
you're basically carnitineless and
therefore you can't generate um beta
oxidation. The claim here is that
fructose inhibits three specific enzymes
critical to mitochondrial function. The
first enzyme is a famous one called
EMPK. It walks the red carpet in
everything. No, but it is well known in
cell biology because it plays a
significant role in controlling many
aspects of cellular function. It is
often considered a master regulator
simply because it's involved in so many
areas of cell function. You can actually
see that in this illustration right
here. You can see AMPK is in the middle
and then the various enzymes connecting
to the various cellular functions. So
Dr. Lustik is spot on when he says that
EMPK is involved in mitochondrial
function and yes it definitely is
involved in the production of new
mitochondria called mitochondrial
biogenesis. Now the real question is
does it get inhibited by AMPK? Dr. istic
mentions a metabolite of fructose called
methyl glyioxil MGO sits inside thempk
and blocks it like the wrong key sitting
inside a lock. To explain that a bit
further, enzymes have active active
sites essentially a groove or pocket
within the enzyme that binds to its
specific substrate and converts it to
another molecule. It's how the enzyme
actually performs its main function.
What Dr. istic is saying is that the
metabolite of fructose MGO sits inside
that pocket bound to arginine particular
amino acids found inside the pocket and
blocks the real substrate of AMPK from
engaging with AMPK since MGO is blocking
the way this effectively neutralizes
AMPK so I tried finding evidence of this
and I couldn't find any I did find a
publication that discusses it but the
discussion was purely hypothetical this
hypothesis does indicate MGO binding
EMPK and it does indicate binding at the
arginines. You can see that the enzyme
structure on the left and then the
structure split into three domains. And
then zooming into the gamma domain like
Dr. Lustik mentioned is the pocket with
the arginine residues. So that all
checks out. But again, there's no
definitive evidence that this occurs and
the paper never discusses fructose as
far as I could tell. So, while the exact
mechanism described may not be backed by
firm evidence, that doesn't mean that
Dr. Lustik is wrong about fructose
inhibiting AMPK as a whole.
Unfortunately, I'd love to tell you a
cleancut story that fructose inhibits
AMPK activation. But while there are
studies that indicate that to be the
case, there are also studies that
suggest that fructose enhances AMPK
activation. Why? is likely contextbased
depending on the tissue that you're
testing, the conditions and more. Now,
in the end, when it comes to cell
biology, things get pretty complex. And
there's another way to probe this that's
more definitive, which I'll get to
later. For now, let's just say that
fructose has mixed evidence on whether
it inhibits or encourages AMPK
activation. And the discrepancy likely
depends on a variety of factors like
tissue type. Let's go on to the next
enzyme before we circle back to a more
definitive answer. The second enzyme is
called AAADL L or ASL COA dehydrogenase
longchain. Forget the name, it doesn't
matter. This enzyme, as Dr. Lustik
pointed out, takes fat molecules and
begins cutting sections off the fat
molecule to feed them into a wood
chipper that we call the mitochondrian.
The mitochondrian eventually uses those
cleaved fat fragments from the fat
molecule and you utilizes it for energy
generation. Now, interestingly, again,
it's not a simple story because the
studies looking at the impact of
fructose on this enzyme, they indicate
that a non-fattening diet plus fructose
has no effect. Yet, a fattening diet
plus fructose does indicate inhibition
of the enzyme. This is also shown in
other studies as well. I'll quick cover
the last enzyme. It's called CPT-1 and
it's basically a gatekeeping protein. It
interacts with fat molecules and allows
them into the mitochondrian so long as
they have a tag like an ID. Obviously,
the mitochondrian can't break down fat
for energy if the fat molecules aren't
allowed in the first place. However,
here again, the same studies indicate
even less convincing evidence that
fructose has no impact on CPT-1
inhibition. The impact is solely driven
by a fattening diet independent of
fructose. Look, ultimately, while there
is evidence against Dr. Lustik's claims,
I should point out again that cell
biology is incredibly complex and it is
highly dependent on the context being
studied. So, I wouldn't consider this a
settled case. I think it's always better
to define the context that you're
discussing and then leave room for
studies that might butt up against that
context. For example, if I say in the
liver in a junk food diet, fructose may
reduce the activity of an enzyme AADL,
then I've defined a narrow band that is
true to a specific study that I've read.
However, if I use much wider
interpretations of fructose always
inhibits a L, then I'd be wrong if I go
to different tissues like the heart or
the brain. and I'd be wrong every time a
study shows otherwise. That's why I like
how a lot of scientists talk. The data
suggests I've seen instances in the
liver under these specific circumstances
there is evidence that it leaves room
for development. But you probably don't
care about that. You just want to know,
does fructose harm my mitochondria,
punk? Give it to me straight.
This is ultimately what we care about,
not the enzymes. We want to know the
actual effect. Well, if I take some of
my own medicine, which tastes like
Pepto-Bismol, I'll put it to you like
this. Very simply, there is some
evidence that fructose does reduce
mitochondrial activity as well as
mitochondrial biogenesis. In the end, we
end up at the same destination. Fructose
probably isn't great for mitochondrial
health, though the mechanisms are a bit
all over the place and likely depend on
more context than what we can cover here
with due diligence. But Dr. Huberman
asks a very important question which
ties into the long-term effects of
fructose consumption.
>> You said fructose inhibits all three of
these enzyatic pathways. Yeah.
>> As a biologist, I have to ask, you know,
how potently does it inhibit them? I
mean because there's there are drugs
that block receptors and then there are
drugs that block receptors with in
unbelievable affinity. So you know I
mean mechanistically in a dish meaning
in vitro you can see all sorts of things
but how how significant is this for like
for obesity for mitochondrial function
in vivo in us. All right. So, look, you
know, the the dose determines the
poison, right? Paraselis 1537.
Um, there are toxins that are parts per
billion and will kill you like sarin,
rice, cyanide. By the way, cyanide is a
good analogy because it's working on
mitochondria. It's basically causing
mitochondria to be completely defective.
>> All right. Then there are um
intermediate toxins like arsenic and
carbon tetrachloride parts per million
and they take a little longer to work.
They're not going to kill you on the
spot.
>> That's why I can eat an apple seed that
has a little bit of arsenic in it but
I'm not going to die.
>> Right? And then finally there and by the
tobacco smoke goes in there. And then
finally you have um uh weak toxins. All
right. And you know where it's not one
exposure that will kill you. It's, you
know, 10,000 exposures that'll kill you.
Like alcohol
>> or toxic people.
>> Yeah. Toxic. Well, some
>> sometimes it only takes one.
>> I couldn't resist. Sorry. Sometimes
it'll mildly toxic people.
>> Anyway, the point is that fructose is in
that last category.
>> So, it's not what you do one day that
kills you. It's what you do every day
that kills you.
And if you basically eat ultrarocessed
food high in sugar for 10 years in a
row, it's going to show up in terms of
your coorbidities and ultimately yeah,
it will kill you. This is an important
concept though probably on some level
obvious. The issue is how potent of a
poison is fructose. Obviously, it isn't
on the same level as cyanide with
instant death. And this is a good point
where Dr. realistic pulls back and
points out that the poisonous nature is
mild. I like and appreciate this
reframing by both. But this raises a
bigger issue then. Does fructose kill us
in the long term? Well, there's plenty
of evidence looking at fructose or
fructose adjacent relationships to all
cause mortality. There are some issues
with these types of studies in singling
fructose's relationship to mortality,
but the evidence definitely suggests
fructose increases our risk of death
from all causes. And I will add that the
the effect is mild, which would speak to
Dr. Listik's point that it is not
potent, but could be drawn out over
time. I will quick add here that if you
were to only focus on randomized control
trials, you would find mixed results.
some finding harm of fructose and some
finding no harm. This usually depends on
the outcome tested in the study
methodology. In the end, I think it's
pretty safe to say that fructose
consumption is a net negative for health
and studies lean in the direction of
increasing mortality risk. All of this
confirms Dr. Lustik's perspective.
Ultimately though, Dr. Lustik points out
how fructose affects our entire
population and the impact that it has on
our lifespan. So, let's get into that.
Now, before we do, if you're looking for
a deeper dive on these concepts, like
understanding how the master enzyme AMPK
works or how these enzymes interact with
our mitochondrial health or how fructose
raises our risk of mortality and more,
then check out the extended version of
this video that you're watching. It's
included for the Physiionic Insiders, my
research platform, including well over
100 health analyses with accompanying
videos and articles, summaries, a
monthly podcast that puts everything
together for you, live sessions with
yours truly, and more. Now, I put a lot
of work into this, and there's more that
I'm not mentioning. I added an AI, a
master supplement list, and more this
year, too. Anyway, I'll shut up, but if
you're interested, join using the link
in the description.
>> And we have the data to show, you know,
how many years you will lose. So, right
now in America, we pay an 8-year
longevity tax. If you look at Japan, who
uh they have a mean age of death of 88.
We have a mean age of 80. Okay? We're
paying an eight-year longevity tax just
by living here. And we're talking about
the healthy people. Now, if you have
metabolic syndrome, it's a 15-year
longevity tax. And uh sorry, if you have
obesity, it's a 15-ear longevity tax.
And if you have metabolic syndrome, it's
a 20-year longevity tax.
That is primarily, not completely, but
primarily sugar.
>> So, the claim is that we Americans are
experiencing an 8-year longevity tax
relative to Japan due to sugar. In fact,
the numbers are a bit different. But
let's not quibble. He's right that
Americans live on average a shorter
lifespan than the Japanese. It's about a
6 years difference. Now, it is
definitely true that the gap expands
with coorbid co-orbidities like
diabetes, cancer, cardiovascular disease
and so on. The big aspect of the claim
is not if the gap is there though, but
that it is at least primarily caused by
sugar consumption. Now, considering the
previous data that we went over, it is
perfectly reasonable to blame fructose
as contributing to a shortened life
expectancy. However, there are many
differences between Japan and the United
States that could not only contribute
but be major factors. For example,
Americans consume 200 to 300 more
calories per day, about 50% more
saturated fat on a percentage basis, and
a bit less dietary fiber. All three of
these are major factors. So, isolating
fructose as the main factor is
presumptuous. I think that it would be
most accurate to say yes, Americans have
a shorter life expectancy compared to
Japanese people and yes, fructose
consumption may be a contributing
factor, but there are undoubtedly
several other factors that likely
contribute significantly. Okay, all that
stated, what are our takeaways here?
Well, Dr. istic is on target with some
like fructose being detrimental to our
health, but does overstate others like
fructose being the main reason for
shortened life expectancy or the
cellular mechanisms of fructose harm.
But here's what can be said. There's
evidence fructose is harmful to
mitochondrial health. Fructose is a
negative to our health and mildly raises
our mortality risk. Fructose consumption
likely contributes to American shortened
life expectancy, but there are highly
likely several other unadressed factors
that also contribute. And now that we've
been discussing fructose in isolation,
but what about in food, like fructose
found in fruits? Well, Dr. Listik
discusses that in this episode of the
centuge along with much more on
fructose. Check it out. I hope this was
informative and I'll catch you in the
next one.